We call it over the right.
It's going to be the Model C Council for Monday, December, 19, 2022.
Two public interference, scheduled personal chances.
We have none.
Three, consent agenda.
Staff, I commend to you.
We are approved items for and by.
Second.
All right.
Step five.
Williams.
Part two.
Part six.
Presentation and vote.
To amend the dollar fifty recreation assessment fee.
Carry over.
And approve this.
The parks.
And sports complex.
Kevin Browney.
Kevin Kiddon.
And Z.
Member Gordon.
Good evening.
We're here.
It's not to give you a little presentation.
To and ask you to amend.
The recreation assessment.
The carry over to expenditure lines in the amount of.
A little over $14,000.
For improvements that will go to sports complex.
This.
Lashpad.
Complex.
And some other areas.
In the city.
This dollar fifty fee was bill.
Just for this reason.
It was for the major pool improvements that happened in 2005.
And it's just in the MSRP program.
So we're not taking money from something that it's not.
It can only be used for these type of product.
So, both of these guys have a little.
Powerpoint.
Just to kind of walk through the projects we're asking for.
If you have any questions about the $1.50 fee, I'll be happy to answer them if I can, you okay?
So where's the $1.50 fee being going before?
It has just been building up year after year after year after year after year.
This is how the sports and rep program got started three or four years ago.
They froze the account and started building the sports program.
And then just this last fiscal year came back to parks when Chuck came to public works.
So it's just now coming back this way.
And that's what Chuck operated on for the last so many years.
Get this sports program built up.
This is on every utility bill, every customer utility bill.
Let's pay it every month.
Thanks.
Yeah.
Thank you.
That.
We do on the night.
Good.
It was like say we've got some projects that we wanted to do here in the city.
I'm going to go over the ones.
They'll do a large bed.
You tell us who you are real quick, you don't mind.
You don't mind.
Everybody on the parks and cemetery manager.
Okay.
That's all right.
You're about four months.
I hadn't seen you before.
I just curious.
All right.
You don't get out much.
You can grow.
So you're seeing years.
This is the type of fence that we're looking to put at.
We're looking to put.
We've had some talk and some concerns from the public about peak kids playing that area and if you guys know that kids can be pretty slippery and they can get out there on the highway.
There's a lot of traffic on that.
So this is the style of fence that we're looking at, you know something that's easy to maintain that we can get underneath the lower.
Toad costs for the fence around $30,000 we'll be looking at.
It's of course what we have currently.
These here are some of the items.
These are some of the items that we're looking at purchased for this splash pad expansion.
You'll see that in the next slide here.
Well these are, these are benches, log stools and planners, as well as cornhole boards.
All these are concrete, so we'll do them in the maintenance.
So we don't have to worry about it.
And they'll be heavy enough that we can just tow them off.
And with the area that we've got out there now with the other learning environment, currently going in.
These kind of follow, the reason we picked these, they kind of follow the same theme is what that is as well as the splash pad.
Are those prefabs?
Yes.
They're all concrete, every fab.
That's what we're just bringing up to this.
The construction of these is the place.
So you can't use those at any time.
Well it's, we do the bags.
I'm not sure if they're that one out yet.
They're all concrete, please.
Yeah.
That's a cup of citrus after we'll do them around.
And then as a corner of the board might be one of those pieces.
But we have with the discipline, of course, out there.
Yeah, here on stuff.
And we have a block.
We've made the board.
The boards.
This is the area here that we're talking about as far as splash pad.
Yeah.
Expansion.
This is just to the west of the large-chain structure there.
There's a large pad.
That's approximately 1,3,3,3,4 feet.
We're going to expect that out.
We're all concrete.
We'll take out the fence.
That concrete fence.
That's what we'll be looking at.
Basically sidewalk.
Do splash pad.
The chain structure there.
And down to the moon.
So you're talking about all the grass area we call the concrete.
Yes. Yes. This whole area here will be excavated out and we put back in the concrete.
And that new fence will start at this entrance when you come into this splash pad.
It will start there and it will run north and it will run all the way down BJ tunnel.
So it will come in. This was a great idea.
But being a concrete fence that doesn't give as kids shake it.
It starts as you can kind of see here. It starts to break out the corners.
And now the panels, the boards, they're supposed to be boards, but they're concrete.
They're starting to come out.
So in something that heavy.
Safety issue there, right?
Yeah.
Thank you very much.
So there won't be a fence across the part of the water.
There will not be one here.
We're going to have to figure something out here in this maybe in areas that we use.
The bench is a log structure or something like that along there.
Keep people going into the thing or for keeping cars to come into it.
That's something we're going to have to look at as with those.
But as far as the along the, you live in this picture here.
This, this is where the fence and the fence and the fence and the fence and the fence and the fence and the fence.
And we'll go back from the north side of this concrete area.
We'll go all the way to BJ tunnel.
And then all the way back to the, to the east to where the new entrance for the upper and bottom is going to be.
Can those, can those kids climb over there?
Hopefully something is going to slow them down.
For sake of, we've had a lot of conversations about the size and style of the fence.
We figure it five foot tall.
Hopefully it'll slow them down enough where they can't.
I mean, we're not obviously it's.
We don't want to put any saying in there that's so tall that it blocks the view and the splash pad.
And, you know, restricts any of that.
The best we can, we're trying to keep it as visually as attractive as we can with it.
How far off of the truck route will be.
As far back enough, we'll be back behind the utility bulls there.
Probably six to eight feet off of that.
So you're probably talking.
I was not actually put in tape measure on it.
You're probably 25 to 30 feet back off of the existing curve.
And that project's just to the concrete alone is going to be about.
$10,800.
Of course, that's what we have.
Was that something the will do or what's contract that out?
We will do the excavation of it.
And as far as you're moving the fence and the excavation of the pad,
we will have a few go towards it.
We'll be doing our concrete for that.
Well, there may be any kind of design in it or anything.
Or just concrete.
It's just going to be a concrete pad.
I mean, basically just filling in this grass area here.
You want your face in there.
We're going to be very relaxed.
We've also been gracious enough to receive a donation from Rotary for $10,000 dollars to place another shake structure like this, which we currently have one out just across the street here at a key club park.
This one we placed over at Rotary Centennial Park, the walking park we have over on, and it'll be just a pretty much a very image of that one right there.
So actually we've got an $10,000 donation out in Rotary, the warm match will be an additional $10,000 to create total of that cost of that project $20.
Where is this going to be located at the park?
Right now if you go, if you were pulled into it, it would be just to the south of that entrance.
We have power supply right there, as you pull in.
So I just turned off the ice street in a way.
Is that central?
Central?
Central and everything.
In a straight into it.
Okay.
That's kind of the proposed spot that we've got because we have close proximity to power.
On my, on my, on your power point here, this says total cost of $10,000.
In the $10,000, but now you're saying it's $20,000.
Yeah, that says something's over in our presentation.
Yeah, I do apologize for that.
Total cost of $20,000.
$10,000 donation.
So basically the city's going to pay 20 and I'm sorry, 10 and Rotary is paying 10.
Why should I do?
Or you do apologize?
I am dead as mine.
So back to the splash pad.
If you guys talked to me about cameras.
There we are.
We have, we have met with the company.
And we actually have a living problem in the tomorrow.
It's in Florida.
It's a cloud-based system where they can run a camera off of a solar panel.
So we have looked at those.
We've got a really close.
Things like that.
And Chuck and Zav and Rodney actually took them all through the city.
Sports complexes and everything else.
So look at that.
And they're supposed to be getting this and members together on that.
Because it's funny.
I got a text from a guy that works for boat.
About 10 days ago.
And he said, hey, is the city talking to somebody about their comic cameras?
I said, not that I've heard of.
Yeah.
And I can't answer that.
And I don't know why he was asking.
So we're going to get more important with boat.
I do that.
It's mobile for a five or a five or a five.
But I don't know what happened, they found another captain coming in to talk to us other than what?
Well, that'd be streamed into our dispatch center for the police department or where we're working with.
I mean, it's a web-based email to talk to us or yes, they can talk to us or yes, they can talk to us or you see it.
So they can actually log into and see the cops coming.
Yep.
So, okay.
Just ask.
Thank you.
Does that thing, I just personally, I think, gotten cameras out there would make it more family safe
than family friendly.
Oh, absolutely.
Yeah, like I said, we took them guys around and took them to all of our different complexes.
That was one of the big things was we talked about the different types of cameras that they had.
You know, the accessibility they had and the features and functions of each one and what would be best for each location.
Well, I'm happy to hear you guys talking about it.
So I look forward to you guys coming back with something for us later.
Any other questions for you?
Thank you.
Thanks.
This is my favorite.
And here are you?
Chuck.
Okay.
And this is not new money, by the way.
We're just moving one and one.
Just so you know.
Oh, me.
All right.
So my focus coming in and board since I've had the taste in the sports world as far as hosting tournaments for the city.
You know, talking about dinner, dinner, dinner, dinner, dinner, dinner, dinner, dinner.
People in the town had a good idea of kind of like what our complexes need.
So, you know, from upkeep and safety standpoint.
So, once I come over here, I kind of put some stuff together.
That was Kevin.
And he was pretty far in a bad at kind of in line of what his daughter envisioned his for our sports and parks.
And so basically my stuff is going to be more of a safety standpoint.
And the actual playability of our kind of voices.
So the first thing I'll shoot with you is fencing.
We've got five fields of softball complexes.
This is more of this one of me towards softball.
And four of the main fields that we use.
The backstop area.
You know, she can see all the pins that stuck in her curl up underneath it.
So that's curling into the field.
So a catcher coming to get the pass ball.
She's sliding into that.
These get in color and these they have to dress this as one of our main focuses is.
And also we're going to add some walk through gates.
So if you've been out through the complex and bit that they're on a Saturday afternoon during our tournaments.
There's only one real good place to get into the fields and that's the dugout.
So what we like to try to do in between games is put the fields.
We chop them, drag them, get them ready for the next game.
Doing that though.
We have to go through the dugout.
So you've got 15 girls trying to get out of the dugout.
That's trying to get in them.
And another 15 other girls trying to get back into the dugout.
So we're going to add some gates.
real close proximity to the dugouts for easy access for mainly build workers, you
publishes an empire just to get through, instead of trying to go through those
dugouts. Because it's quick, we've got a new quick move, just to make it a lot
faster, do it that way. So, after we replaced the back stops that to help make these
things last longer, is what add back stop paddings to all of those fields.
That's because it takes a long, two foot tall. We're actually looking by six
on him, we'll put two on that little baseball, and these will be removable. So when we
get done with them, maybe we're done with the tournament, done with the games, we could
just put them on the fence, take them out from inside the garage, so they'll last
longer, we're not to keep them out in the weather. I'm just saying like that.
We've been right along. The next one is, this is the T-ball field, what we call the
T-ball field, and our robots are called, field number five. It's the outfield
pencil, as you can see. It's like this. You're going to pose to be an over, you've got
actually a pose, I think take pictures of all of them, but they're kind of a part over time.
We could be trippy, it's a lot of things. We get wet out there sometimes, what's out
there sometimes, and we actually don't really use this build right now, just because it
has been missing out there so bad. So we want to replace that out of the building, is part
of that project. If you look at our lot of people, like these two, the old adult fields,
and the travel ball world, and even our local youth, directly, because adult kids don't
people don't put out anymore. There's no adult league or anything like that. So we have used an
orange temporary pencil last four years, because the girls just don't like playing on a 360-by-foot
pencil. So what we've done, we've put this temporary pencil in the end, but there's been okay,
but over time, it's really hard to maintain. It's especially weeding around there because you want
to have to plastic bins. You get a lot of ground roll doubles, it does balls go underneath the
orange kitchen. So we want to add new outpilpising or around, and we will keep, it's hard to see,
I'm sorry guys, but this current outpilpising is because what we'll do is, this will create places
for special link internments for girls and teams to warm up in between before their games.
That's one struggle that a lot of complexes has. It's places for its girls to warm up before their game.
This adds, I mean, you could fit three teams down here, warm up.
to get straight from the next game.
This is just another picture of a back here.
It's just BBC 5, Orange, Fencing.
No, it just doesn't last very long.
This would be a permanent structure.
We want to add to it out there.
The original Fencing bag behind is a good shape.
Good shape.
Get fine.
That's an arm with it really.
We're going to leave it up.
I can say it in that way.
We're just creating a spot for people to warm up.
I mean, I've seen people moms and dads and stuff.
They don't take their chairs and sit back there too.
Because it's out of the plain sight.
So that, for the most part, is for Jewish subwalk on blocks.
Again, live dancing repairs and replacement.
And a few new vintage.
The next one is tennis courts.
People walk courts.
If you remember, we resurface the tennis ball.
Or tennis courts.
And add it six pickle ball courts.
She got three, three.
This would be offensive between those six.
We have to divide it up a little bit.
Keys.
Keys balls and stuff and flying.
Coupled on somebody's court.
And they'll also be a gate in between.
You have about 45 feet on one side.
And the 45 would be over 40 on the other side.
And then you'll have a gate in between it.
The next one is probably the biggest one.
That's the same amount of soccer complex.
Over time, basically playing the surface of that complex is pretty bright.
I mean, if you've been out there in a while, it doesn't drain very well in certain spots.
It's real.
It's got a bunch of dips.
A bunch of low spots, a bunch of high spots.
And she's real on it even.
And grass doesn't grow under very well.
If you try to mow it, I mean, you need to go to your car record the next day.
Get the silver off.
So what we're looking to do and work with soccer superstition.
In the USA, is renovating.
And by renovating this specific start for scratch, we're going to kill them all up.
Spill them all out.
Create a little crown in the middle of each field to where they drain properly.
And we'll re-seal them and fertilize them in the top dress.
We're going to do eight.
This spring, actually, is going to start it already.
And then the eight that we're not working on, we're working on soccer, we'll play on.
And I've got it a little map.
So you wanted to build the red.
But it wants to work for soon to renovate this year.
And it feels in the green.
I can best work soccer in the USA to play during the springtime.
Then the fall of 2023.
The green fields we will renovate.
And then the red fields should be ready to go.
And then to start.
Find it on.
This is all play on the red fields.
It's just kind of a snapshot of what we've already kind of done already.
Well, I've been for warms.
Children all lives, Mrs. All out.
And then we'll actually live a scope to each field too.
We'll put a scope in the middle of it,
so we can make sure that we got proper drainage
and for those fields.
The parks department, it's a good huge cemetery.
We've got a lucky cemetery's cutting in the new road.
They've got tons of dirt to get rid of.
So that's where we're getting a lot of our dirt from them.
The road of harvest kind of helped us with the scope,
and it makes sure we get it to dry and properly.
So that's kind of what I've got.
I mean, I'll move to the next.
You guys got any questions about anything?
I know when to do it. Pretty quick.
On the salt wall deal, we're going to spend a lot of money out there on 15
and stuff like that, let it flood again.
I thought about the other example.
It is a fine line.
It's how much do you want to put it there?
I don't want to put it there.
I won't say the way that the housing is now.
It's probably left here on the home floor.
It's convincing that anything out there,
no fault to anybody.
The sports complex has not been a priority.
You're curing that time.
Now, of course, it's not to be in the main situation
that we're going to add a little bit of focus to those fields.
It's hard to move them.
That's ideally.
But when's ever happened?
Well, what can we take care of now?
And be smart and diligent with it?
Let's turn on the funds of having that dollar 50,
but at the same time, just going to ton of money.
We're out there before tournaments going out there,
fixing that up, missing.
Everyone in the quarter of the tournament,
because it just continues to be used to be used to get worse and worse.
Now, I have a great question.
It's about to want to.
How much? What's that by line?
I agree.
I mean, the city makes a lot of money on tournaments and stuff like that
through the softball association and everything else.
Baseball had probably need to invest a little bit,
but we also maybe need to look in the near future
or maybe something different.
I mean, we're always working at a different place.
There's different angles to be able to move these complexes.
Anything going to the sports club complex is a brass.
It's all a safety issue.
There's no cosmetics going into that.
The parks has a little cosmetics and splash pan, things like that.
And everything you do at the sports complex,
historically from a safety issue.
I could take the answer right now,
and you can say, well, chef,
we'll probably need to request a hold of this.
This is to take care of the needs that really need to be addressed.
It's been a new address for a while.
So those money were originally...
That's dollar pickin' charge was originally weird with this board's company.
No, originally the dollar pickin' was billed for coal improvements and MSRP, and in 2016, it was,
and we ended it to say, sports and rack and parks and rack, so a broad enough want that money to be useful.
But it was always specific for repair and maintenance in parks, pool, MSRP program, and now sports rack.
And Chuck, you're doing a great job, I'm not saying that, and I think we do need a lot of upkeep out there,
but us as the council probably need to look at something in the near future or however long it takes.
To do something different, I mean, I travel a lot with my grandkids and see it, and their fields are twice as good as what we ever thought about.
And they make a lot of money.
You know, I think you're both the more largest complex, as you're out in the middle of the business.
Thanks, Paul.
Yeah, too, the city's horn, going back, starting working for Amanda, the product that we present from a term standpoint, is for good,
just from the feedback that we get, we do a really good job of putting on a term.
As facilities, this is one of the main things that people look at, when they pick a place to go play.
The facilities on ours, and then the communication with the term director, those are the top three things that those people look at.
We've been very fortunate with a lot of the weather events that we're still able to still get a lot of those fields ready.
You play it on for the term, but, you know, from a safety standpoint, you know, looking at that stuff.
And doing tournaments for the last five years, we start doing stuff like that.
People from back, okay, we're going to put just up back into what they've generated over the last four or five years from the revenue standpoint.
So I think that goes to the speaks of all these as well.
There's come to total amounts.
This is what's currently roughly, you know, you know, two 91, one, one, say five a set in that fund.
This is the amount that we're asking for.
Or at least it's still still pretty healthy.
So we're not depleting that fund.
Okay, something that you're about to pull or something like that.
We still have a buffer and that.
I have a phrase too.
I was just going to ask you about that. So you had 10, 6, 9.
Yeah, that's just one.
So I'll come back.
Thanks.
You would probably be close, right?
10, 10, 10.
So I like to say, Chuck, you're doing a great job.
I love the fact that you're going to talk to fields, because they are pretty bad.
Especially when it rains, it's just a mess out there.
And some of that you're addressing that is that you're doing a great job.
The crew really likes it.
They like the direction you're taking them.
They like your leadership, so they're doing a great job.
So I think the teams get to build.
It's a really nice and good stuff happened here.
So, but what I like to ask is we brought up from stuff about the fields and moving them.
It's something that somebody is a brand of.
You know, we want to figure out how to fund them.
But if we start putting that stuff into work, some of what we want to do, where we want to go,
then we start worrying about funding and how to get it done there.
Right now we've got $291,000 in that fund.
I mean, that's going to go a little way.
Is it's not going to go what we need, but it will help.
And I said, I'm really about $169 roughly to take a dollar to you.
And I'm sure it's about a more expensive than we know.
But it doesn't even feel it's a work.
I like that.
If I were to put a set and then a softball field.
That's the complex where it's at now.
This was three years ago.
Thank you.
It was probably around $4.50.
That's fancy.
Somebody come in and do the action.
There were no, not really any city money for city labor.
But we're putting advanced dugouts, environment and so on.
$25.50,000.
Yeah, just for field.
Perfield.
Three years ago.
So it's doubled now.
Exactly.
I mean, you look at Seneca.
The little town of Seneca.
And they're fields all as true turf.
And the old nine yard for baseball field.
I mean, come on.
Yeah.
No way.
No.
No, you're not.
So we've got to momentum right now from a thermostat.
And then we've seen stuff like this.
We'll help.
And then I think they were the ones.
We all know that travel ball tournaments bring in that revenue.
Absolutely.
From the tax place.
I've seen a lot of times.
I think we've done a pretty good job.
We've done some bar.
We've got a great team in the last four, five years.
We do that with.
We start seeing stuff like that.
Teaser on nuts.
And maybe we can partner with somebody else.
But I heard.
I heard you guys have.
Check out the tournament.
To just buzz out there for 30 minutes or something.
And look at the people that are there and listen.
Listen a few of the folks.
They're excited about being here.
They love the fact that Chuck does a great job out there.
And I know.
If you try to go in.
Not to grocery.
It's a problem.
There's a lot of the door.
People get things.
We just do.
We just don't know.
We're just telling you exactly.
We just don't.
So the last thing, this will be the position of what help us put together in a story, but
this happens probably, because I don't know that anybody's ever kind of right now, we're
not all of you, if you go in, that they tell you about what they're doing, so we're going
to be able to tell them exactly this is what we're doing with your life.
We're listening, you say you can get things in a splash pad or less if you're not going to
go with it.
You know, we're going to have a part page, you know, you get on our several times, you know,
I'll post it stuff when they're going to share it at the time.
So this will come from the city page who are more in debt than what we're actually dealing with.
And what we're talking about part, we need to think about autism, the kids with autism
and building parks for the building, they park for them.
We've been in contact with a couple of different people and programs at looking at locations
for that.
Something not around water or highways or anything like that.
We actually live in a way in that.
Yeah.
Good.
So it's kind of give you some perspective on the dollar fifty feet, you're talking
to sixty-seven thousand meters that we have that are being charged to dollar fifty per month.
So you're generating around 116,000 per year that dollar fifty feet.
We can do some stuff.
That's why we're going to get some plans and let's try to make this thing move and then I'm
going to want to have a problem is where.
So we're sitting on some property out there so I'm not sure if you can help them figure out
what those are.
Who's in the Christy Man, but I know we also have some parcels on and I don't know where you
want to put them or not, but if we got some stuff we already know, might be a place to start
looking.
When we talk often about getting rid of some property too that we're not utilizing and so
the goal would be kind of like, you start about that.
Focus, parks.
We've got to do a lot of clean-up.
We've got to go through the property that we're maintaining now that we don't need to own
this city and then that will give us more opportunity to take care of maintaining properly
focus parks.
We're talking about here.
Whether that be a sports complex, or if you're just talking park, no one a thousand acres.
So yeah.
Just the last question I have, is this something that we're voting on right now tonight?
I mean, I noticed that it's an action item, so we're voting to approve everything that
they presented to us.
Okay.
I just wanted to be clear.
You're a lot of them.
I'll make a motion.
Whatever.
So we approve this tonight when you start on it, if we don't expect it to be completed.
I'll start moving tomorrow with the quotes that I've been having.
We're more of a team.
All of our quotes made up thing out.
We'll start following the trigger.
Well, the fence would be done before.
the next season you think before splash that season.
I'm probably out in the harbor like our playground equipment.
It is in that.
Why I'll make the motion.
I'll second.
Hi.
Thank you guys.
I appreciate it.
Thank you.
Good job, gentlemen.
The great boat on the city of my film permit.
The law tourism department, the finalized application.
Hi.
We miss seven.
Thank you.
This is a budget amendment.
This is the first part of the amendment.
There are four parts.
The first part is a correction from a previous amendment.
A amendment 23-07.
It was the one where the 911 board gave money.
Additional money in stipends to the dispatchers.
This is a line missing.
There should have been a line that added the revenue.
So this is just correcting that and making sure it's all dressed right dressed in the budget.
The second set of numbers is ARPA.
ARPA told us how much we were going to get.
But we got more than they said than we budgeted.
We got $10,835 and 46 cents more than they had told us originally.
So we are asking that that money is put towards street repair.
That's what's proposed on this amendment.
We're not done.
We got two more.
I knew you would.
The third one is the first part of the Code Compliance Community Development.
Vehicle Swap and Purges.
The SUVs.
And then the fourth part is the $1.50 spending of the carryover.
And the SUV is we purchase those two, right?
We're purchasing two.
We're transferring.
Yes, but it is not additional.
It is not additional.
You budgeted.
This is what we just voted for an MSU.
Yes, it's the second.
It's the first part of that.
Oh, my question.
Second.
Hi.
Thanks.
All right.
Now I'm a great fellow.
I'm a city of my film.
Permit to allow tourism department to analyze application or film family certification for the city of mine.
Good evening.
So we are excited about a new kind of a new industry.
It's a statewide thing initiative that's happening.
So we're talking a lot about spending money.
So this is kind of to follow up to talk about ways that we can bring in.
Even new dollars.
So before we dive into it.
This is kind of...
I'm going to show you guys a video so the Department of Commerce produced this about a year ago and this is what they've been out in communities that has to do with this film-friendly certification that we're going to talk about.
So before that we have the production bits, you know, they say action and other cool stuff like that.
And we all know that I'm just going to think those hundreds of meals come from three times a day.
That's right, our local business. We've just added at least another 30 jobs.
We need cost-to-design, Rob's purchased, and air-made, and lots, and lots of stuff.
So we've got the 500, we need 500 of them, but we're all the costumes, we're all the actors, and the special effects, music, and all the games and the location.
So on to the location.
I heard you guys said it.
We're all all right.
Wait, why don't we go home up?
There's so many places to film.
Some of your favorite movies, and some of our states, and others.
So it kind of just gives you guys a little bit of an overview and the importance of really kind of a new industry, that the Department of Commerce has tackled over the years.
So it kind of just gives you guys a little bit of an overview and the importance of really kind of a new industry that the Department of Commerce has tackled over the last few years.
They have started a new program, so you are seeing municipalities all over the state that are
becoming film-friendly certified.
So the city in Miami will be known as a film-friendly certified community, and why that's
important for us is the legislators, and we talked about this in staff the other day, been
was a part of this when it was first introduced.
They have $30 million that's been into an account every year in Oklahoma City.
So for instance, Killers of the Fire Moon, which was just filmed in Pahaskin, and Bartles
Field was a huge impact for that region.
They can apply for incentive, so they come and spend so much money to produce this film
in Oklahoma.
The state gives them some incentive money back.
So one of the things, though, that they have to have, as part of their application to
the state, for this incentive program, is they have to have film permits.
So that's why it's important for this certification.
So what you guys have is you have the copy of what our film permit is going to look like, and we basically
Lauren and I, and Sherry as well before she retired, had really looked at a lot of different
communities.
So we pulled information we liked from Guthrie, which Guthrie is having movies left and right.
Tulsa, which is now produced, they've now started their own film and music offices, a part
of the city of Tulsa, and then Bartlesville, which has really kind of been a city that's
been extremely progressive.
We just pulled different things from all of their permits, and you guys have that in your
packet.
So a production company, if they come in, and they know that they're going to be a part
of the incentive, we will be known as a film-friendly certified community.
They will have that permit that will go into their packets.
So I can tell you, you know, I mentioned that movie a minute ago, when they first started
doing that movie, and we fart, you know, State Tourism Board, we knew it was coming.
It was called Grey Horse for a long time.
It didn't have a title because the confidentiality, and their early estimates was about
$25 million economic impact, the end of that being $40 million dollars, and that's for the
Pheeska and Bartlesville area.
You couldn't get a hotel, you just, you know, I've said it, I feel like for two or three years,
there's no warehouse space in the city of Bartlesville right now.
So we talked about all of our empty buildings that are here.
We know it's coming on the tourism side, you know, Kevin Chers, our tourism board, and we've
talked that length over the last few years about when we monitor and look at analysis
of states, we're typically Oklahoma, Texas, Arkansas, Missouri, and Kansas, strong,
people requesting information.
Over about the last two years, we've seen California jump into the top 10, over the last year,
California's now in our top five.
So we know that we've got people coming over here, there's a lot of people relocating to Oklahoma.
So I love the opportunity that it presents to us as a city as a region.
The states are already doing it, they're already coming to North East Oklahoma.
The Cherokee Nation, if you guys follow them in the news, they've just put a, and there's
came from the used ARPA funding for that, but they put a huge amount of funding into a new indoor
sound stage.
Chickasal Nation has done the same thing, the city.
of Tulsa is getting ready to do a huge development
along with some Route 66 incentives that they're doing as well.
So if you really look at it,
statewide, they're migrating to North East Oklahoma.
So they're coming, I mean, they're going to be coming here.
We're going to start seeing carry over.
So this is just kind of the first step.
I'd love to be able to come back and, you know,
six or eight months and let you guys know
that we've been doing site visits
and we've got some production companies
that's going to be coming in here.
And hopefully, you know, my ML will be in the news
like Bartosville's and the news.
But you have all the information.
You also have a little bit of a sheet
that talks about the economic impact.
And the fact of, again, what it did for just the dollars
into the city of Bartosville, it was $367,000 in sales tax
and an additional $150,000 in large tax,
which would make it pretty substantial impact
for our budget as well.
So that's what I have for you guys tonight
is just for you to approve this film permit
that will allow us to finalize our package.
And we will submit all that stuff this week.
And get it all into the Department of Commerce
and hopefully get something fairly quickly.
That will show the city of Miami certified.
I don't want another upside of it.
Amanda, tell us a little bit about which we talked in our committee.
But when they come in and do renovations
and stuff like that for movies,
they don't take it back out.
They give it to us.
So yeah, thank you for mentioning that.
So recently, if you guys followed like hallmark channel
and Christmas movies, you'll know that the city of Claremore
just partnered with I call her DJ Tanner
because if you watched Full House, she was DJ Tanner,
but her production crew just came in the Claremore
and they did a Christmas movie about three months ago,
came in and basically decorated the entire city of Claremore
about all Christmas decorations decorated their poles.
So everything that they brought in to the city of Claremore
when they finished that up, they left it all.
They donated it all to the city of Claremore.
So now they have all brand new Christmas decorations.
And then killers of the Fire Moon, you can go and Google that
when they were using downtown Fairfax
is like their main area that they were filming this movie.
They ran in and re-did all the empty storefronts,
went in and the outside of them, made them look like brand new,
spent huge amounts of dollars to do.
It's really economic development for downtown Fairfax
and then when they left, all those buildings are all brand new.
And that was the donation of those production companies.
I mean, those are just two stories
that you can Google and read about it.
I'm sure there's much more of things that they're leaving behind
after they've done a movie.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Excuse me.
You said tomorrow's little, okay,
on any warehouse space, before they were.
Costumes, site, stage supplies, a little bit of everything.
So Apple has pretty much come in and dominated.
They've kind of put their flag and bottles fill,
that they've kind of made it their new home.
Paramount Plus, if you guys are on social media,
you know that Rocky was here.
not too long ago doing some scenes at the old Mickey
Manel Home.
He was here doing that.
So Paramount Plus has kind of teamed up
with the city of Tulsa in the film and music office there.
And they've kind of put their flag in Tulsa.
And you've got to think of all the difference.
We all have the streaming services.
We all watch all of them.
So you've got Apple and Paramount Plus.
That's kind of put their flag in Oklahoma.
And we all know there's a whole lot more
that's going to be looking for home.
So I mean, I'm excited about it.
I know we were talking and stabbed the other day.
And Melinda had shared she had some family.
I think that went to Bartlesville.
Yeah, that worked on some of those movies and sets.
And they pay them.
So those are people that are picking up additional ways to make money.
So you're going to have all those additional people.
But you're also going to have the people.
We talked about it and stabbed the other day.
I said, I hope that we're having this conversation in two years.
Talking about we have all these 20 and 30
roads that have relocated here that are part of production teams.
And we're trying to figure out what are they going to do?
Either here.
And it just continues kind of that domino effect.
And it continues to do some things to help us kind of plan and develop more.
So once we get this permanent out there, what happens next?
We get busy on sets just another kind of part of our sales package.
Just we're selling the city.
We start identifying production companies.
We will go into a database with the Department of Commerce.
So if somebody says, which I can't tell you how many side visits we've done over the last three
to four years of just the Coleman.
I mean, it's probably 30, a minimum of 30, with production companies and people that
are leads that are going out looking for locations that.
So we will upload what we will identify as our top 15, maybe top 20 locations that we felt like.
Or we feel like would be ideal for a movie, you know, the Coleman Theatre.
We talk about the Buffalo outside of town, all those different things where production companies
would be interested in that.
And that will all be in the database that they'll be able to pull from.
And then now with having the film permit, it's going to open us up to some bigger production
companies.
It's going to show them that we're, that my MS series about the film industry.
And is the county and other cities are looking at the same contract we have.
So the county have been working with them.
So once you guys approve this, we will take the same template to the county and they'll update that
on their side legally for this to be the same thing that they use for auto-accounting.
Commissioner Furnace and I probably about a year ago worked with the production company.
And we, they were honest because they wanted the film permit.
Well, it's because they wanted to be able to apply for the States and Senate.
So we'll work very closely with the county when we really start launching this and get aggressive
that will, those communication ties between us and the county, they'll be really strong.
Like a motion to breathe.
Sick.
Hi.
Thank you.
Thank you, ma'am.
Now, I will on the recommendation from the city zoning and planning to mission to
reason lots one group four, box 27, original plot one, box five, two, six,
block 27, original plot one, from residential multi-family, deep commercial,
professional office.
It's Christie.
Yeah.
I mean, Christie, she did.
So these are the vacant properties that are north of Alex Acupand's office on a Northwest.
And there's had a hearing public hearing at the city zoning and planning commission
meeting.
We didn't have anybody in attendance to oppose the development and the committee voted unanimously
to make the recommendation to change the zoning.
There's two of these properties.
Yeah.
There's six lots right there together and so there's going to be one office building there.
It's the whole area.
That one space north of Alex's house?
Yes.
Yeah.
All the grass area.
It's been vacant for a long time.
Yeah.
Well, I just run the time.
We have two tonight.
Okay.
I like most of them.
Hi.
And 10.
Still Christie.
Yes.
No recommendations from city zoning and planning commission.
There is 1850 agencies from residential single family.
For residential multi-family.
I'm going to bring more than 0.22 to 18.
All right.
We have Matt Whalen here tonight representing Robbie Payne.
Sorry.
Good evening.
If you have any questions about this project.
But this is another vacant piece of property that's been vacant for a long time.
And we've gotten several complaints about overgrowth on the property in the past.
That Robbie Payne has purchased and is going to be putting a duplex on that if the zoning
is approved.
This is behind that committee.
Yeah.
I see.
There's no pushback.
It's the necessary right behind the committee.
It's the one that has the little time.
Well.
Street.
There's an alley.
There's all down there in the right amount.
Yes.
And Darrell.
Darrell didn't have any problems with the rezoning.
Yeah.
So you got this right away, man.
Well, we had a public session, and I want to show it up.
Yeah.
We had a public hearing on this also, and we didn't have anybody show up.
So he wouldn't anticipate he pushed back me on the neighbors that had no.
No.
I mean, you know, everything probably does.
I don't know.
You know, he does as well.
I mean, he's going to go in and have some properties.
Yeah.
I mean, he's going to tear it down.
I don't know.
It's from the past.
We provided plans.
I think you got a copy of that.
Yeah.
So I can't take it out.
I got to leave it.
And he's going to do it.
And you got to leave that tree right on the core.
I'll just go with the bulletin.
Well, actually, that's not on his property.
Yes.
He has the property across the street.
Okay.
That's the one across the street with all the other trees.
Yes.
That's just a miniature cherry.
It is.
It's so funny.
It's been up for years.
Yes.
Then that really nice thing about both of these.
Resonings or these are vacant properties that haven't had utility customers on them for years.
That's actually $3 dollars.
You said there was plans for this.
Yeah.
They should be.
It's a duplex.
No.
Or the plans.
They should be in your packet.
It's on this supplemental document, right?
Yeah.
I would do that.
I think that page is missing.
Because when we did it in the zoning and plainboard,
there was a drawing.
Uh-huh.
A drawing is not in here.
There it is.
That's it.
Well, you said it's a duplex.
It is.
That's more 50.
For the team.
All right.
It's a long office building.
I'll make motion.
All right.
Thank you. Thanks, Matt. Thanks, Matt.
Art, Judge. Sorry.
Not yet. Almost.
Not yet.
We can have.
Thanks, Matt.
And we're letting authorized to call it cross claim.
We will also call it, but I've mentioned bank.
Normally, that was a bank that wanted to lock the four clothes.
It's mortgage against the David Boehler.
I will count on KC3, CJ-022-011,
and authorized the mayor to sign, say.
So the bank filed a mortgage foreclosure on four different pieces of property.
Interestingly, I'm not sure how you foreclose in a district court of Ottawa County,
a piece of property that's in Missouri, but they did.
But that's not our issue.
Of the four pieces of property, one of them is here in Miami,
and we have three different abatement leans against the property.
The interesting thing is that the total of those three leans is $1,200 in filing a cross claim
against the property owner.
Personally, we would be seeking that $1,200, plus change, with interest and attorney's fees.
The reason why this one is important, this particular property owner
has had several pieces of property here in Miami.
Right now, we think that in a cursory look, there are four other leans
that we can readily find.
We just changed the system of how we're doing this about two years ago,
and so from two years ago to present,
it's easy for us to find the information.
Those leans, which are not part of what we're talking about,
but I just want you to understand the background here,
those leans are about $20,000.
And then we know that there are a number of other leans
that this particular property owner has had,
where he also didn't pay his taxes,
and so those properties all went to the county,
but as was the practice for many, many years here,
whenever property went to the county,
we just released our leans.
We don't have to do that.
Well, we have to release our leans,
but we still would have a legal right to proceed
against the property owner.
And yet, a judgment against that person in persona,
and this is what the law says.
I'm giving you all that information to show you that this is one of
of those property owners that we have in this city
that doesn't take care of the property.
They expect the taxpayers to take care of the property for them.
And then whatever profits they get, whatever rents they get, they pocket that and walk away
and leave the county holding the bag for everything else.
So I don't know how much in total this particular property owner may owe the city.
We know it's going to be more than $20,000.
This is the only one that we can do in this lawsuit, but that's what we're asking you to
allow us to start proceeding against those types of scenarios.
So it's not this one, this one.
There will be more, but all we're asking for right now is this particular $1,200.
So you're asking us to pursue them.
This one.
We're going to be able to pursue them.
We're asking you to allow us to proceed on this one, but I'm just giving you the information
that the intent, unless you tell us otherwise, that we're wanting to start, we're refining
our process.
And this is a step in doing that, where we can go against those types of property owners on other instances
and recover the taxpayers money for the city.
If you're saying every dime you'll come to us, that's all the bond out of you.
Yeah.
So this one is a cross claim.
To just defend the lawsuit that's been filed against this, we don't need your permission.
I don't need your permission.
I'm supposed to do that.
But for us to take an affirmative action against somebody else in it, we do need your permission.
I'd like the lawsuit that I talked to you about a couple of weeks ago.
We will have no cost in it.
The filing fees have already been paid by the bank, the plaintiff, in this case.
It's just authorizing me to pursue it, you decide the cross claim, which we have, if that's authorized.
And we'll get it filed this week and go from there.
I'll make a motion to approve.
Sorry.
Hi.
Williams.
Peace.
Hi.
12.
Do you business at any, which is a residence in the post office agenda?
13.
Mayor.
Council.
Okay.
I got some.
Great.
First, I want to say Molly.
Great job.
The employee and retiree.
Dinner.
I want to put Christmas dinner or holiday dinner.
But Molly worked our child in off and pulled off a great event.
So I want to tell you, thank you.
Her law of good feedback from their retirees.
They really appreciate it.
I don't know you.
I don't think that's been done in a long time, hasn't?
The long time, long time.
I know Linda had mentioned probably the last person I talked to.
Remembered having one, and she said that was.
Many, many, many city managers go.
So, kind of the 10, 20 years.
Good job.
Thank you.
That was good.
Appreciate it.
Appreciate your efforts.
You're probably ahead of us.
Thank you.
A little.
Four teams.
They managed from the occasion.
I would certainly echo everything you said.
And just for everyone, this will be our last meeting of this.
Calendar year.
So, our next meeting will not be until the third of January.
So, hope everybody has a safe holiday, safe travels.
We do have some interesting weather coming this Thursday.
So, be weather aware.
But it's snow.
It happens.
Right now, we have the potential three to four inches of snow.
I hope it's going to top of that.
It's going to be brutally cold.
That's what makes it very difficult when we have snow.
And then we have cold and Tyler could echo this or provide better details.
But, you know, throwing salts on a road that, you know,
tin below doesn't really help.
That doesn't do anything.
It just melts and releases.
Just leave it.
Everybody's going to be on.
Off anyway.
Sometimes.
Just leave.
So, it'll be another thing.
We need to do clearing while trying to keep the roads clean.
And I know there's going to be a lot of people trying to travel.
But bear with us.
The officers are closed Friday in Monday after the holiday.
Friday and four Monday after.
We'll see what the weather does.
The weather may shut us down early on Thursday.
We're already closed on Friday, which is good.
So, people won't be out in it.
But, did I hear?
I hear a wind tune.
Twenty to thirty below.
Yeah.
The high, like Thursday's four.
So, and then we're out.
So, I'm in.
I can.
I don't know.
We also just remember that our police fire will definitely be out.
I'll be out.
I'll get to stay home.
Right.
But so, I've got that.
So, first.
That's a great point, Mayor.
Our first responders will be out there.
And thank you guys.
Yeah.
Hi.
When the rest of us are home, trying to stay out of it and stay warm and muddle up.
All the days.
I know our guys have to be out there prepared to respond to the moment's notice.
I'll be with you.
Whether that be a first responder of fire police or...
water and this is what happens, right? This is what we have. Major water breaks is what it gets this cold and those guys have to go
Stated a gushing water and or sewer. You see and so
God bless all of these people that keep this this city moving
We certainly appreciate it and can't say enough now. All that they do keep the electric on keep the water running
keep the sewer moving out and keep a safe so
Never appreciate
All right 15 adjourn it. Some move. Second of the clothes.
But I
So let's just read the player